Guide to the A. W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Records, 1930-1980 AIS.1980.29
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Cultural, XI.
  - Pittsburgh, Children's Museum (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Pittsburgh, Ballet Theatre (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Pittsburgh, Council for the Arts (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Pittsburgh, Dance Council (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Pittsburgh, Drama League (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - Pittsburgh, Graphics Workshop (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Opera Studies, 1977-1978 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Pittsburgh
    - Opera, Inc., financial (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Oratorio Society (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Playhouse (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Public Theater (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Soceity of Artists (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Youth Symphony Orchestra Association (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Symphony (Box 33, Folder 9-10)
  - American Poetry Review (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Point Park College (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - Renaissance and Baroque Society (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - Renaissance Center for the Arts (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - Theater Dance (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - TRIAD (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Vanguard Theatre (Box 34, Folder 2)
- Education, XII.
  - Carnegie Mellon University (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Chatham College (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Robert Morris College (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - University of Pittsburgh (Box 34, Folder 6-9)
- Miscellaneous Reports and Publications, XIII.
  - Urban Redevelopment Authority (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Materials Removed from safety deposit boxes of the A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - By Laws of the A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Deed of the Trust (Box 35, Folder 2-4)
  - Orphans Court Material (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Annual Financial Reports, 1961-1977 (Box 35, Folder 6-8)
  - Financial Statements, Price, Waterhouse, and Co., 1964-1978 (Box 35, Folder 9-11)
  - Form 990, Federal Information Return, 1974-1977 (Box 35, Folder 12-15)
  - Custodian Account No. 075-Q38, Agreement and General Correspondence (Box 35, Folder 16)
  - Allegheny County Parks, Acquisition of land (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Shanahan Transfer and Storage Co., Inc. (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Pitt Professorships and Grants (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Carnegie Mellon Capital (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - National Gallery of Art, Schedule 3, Confidential (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - University Professors Dealing with Psychological Physics (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Subject Reports on Endowed Professorship and Fellowships at the University of Pittsburgh and Carnegie Mellon University (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Historical Perspectives in Parapsychology, R.A. McConnell,ed. (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Proposal from Carnegie Mellon University to A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust, 1978 (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - Carnegie Mellon Undergraduate Catalog, 1970-1980 (Box 36, Folder 10)
  - Carnegie Mellon University, The Professional Choice (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - Arts Management Research and Service Center, 1977 (Box 36, Folder 12)
  - Carnegie Insitute of Technology, Educational Papers (Box 36, Folder 13)
  - Washington and Jefferson College Catalogue, 1979-1980 (Box 36, Folder 14)
  - St. John's College, 1979-1980 (Box 36, Folder 15)
  - Downtown at Carnegie Mellon, College of Fine Arts (Box 36, Folder 16)
  - Carnegie Mellon University, Humanities and Social Sciences, Undergraduate Catalogue, 1979-1981 (Box 36, Folder 17)
  - Carnegie Mellon University Financial and Statistical Report, 1979 (Box 36, Folder 18)
  - Carnegie Mellon University Report of the President for the Academic School Year, 1978-1979 (Box 36, Folder 19)
  - University of Pittsburgh Bulletin, The College of Arts and Sciences, 1975-1977 (Box 36, Folder 20)
  - Chatham College, Academic Bulletin, 1979-1980 (Box 36, Folder 21)
  - Allegheny College Catalogue, 1979-1980 (Box 36, Folder 22)
- Contributions, 1930-1970; XIV.
  - Allegheny County Jail (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - American Cancer Society (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Action Housing, Inc., Allegheny Council to Improve Our Neighborhood Housing, Inc. (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - American Council on NATO, Inc. (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - American Chemical Society, Pittsburgh Section (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - American Council to Improve Our Neighborhoods (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - American Law Institute (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - American Nuclear Society (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - American Red Cross (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - American Wind Symphony (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Art Society of Pittsburgh (Box 37, Folder 11)
  - Atlantic Council of the United States (Box 37, Folder 12)
  - Atlantica Foundation (Box 37, Folder 13-14)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, A (Box 37, Folder 15)
  - Boys Club of Pittsburgh, Inc. (Box 37, Folder 16)
  - Boy Scouts of America, Allegheny County Council (Box 37, Folder 17)
  - Brookings Institution (Box 37, Folder 18-19)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, B (Box 37, Folder 20)
  - Carlow College (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Childrens Hospital of Pittsburgh (Box 38, Folder 2-3)
  - Civic Light Opera of Pittsburgh (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Community Chest of Pittsburgh (Box 38, Folder 5-12)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, C-E (Box 38, Folder 13)
  - Carnegie Institute (Box 38, Folder 15-17)
  - Carnegie Institute (Box 39, Folder 1-19)
  - Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh (Box 40, Folder 1-2)
  - Carnegie Institute of Technology (Box 40, Folder 3-16)
  - Chatham College (Box 41, Folder 1-18)
  - Fort Ligonier (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, F (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Gallinger Hospital, Washington, D.C. (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - George Washington Foundation (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - George Washington University Hospital (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, G (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Harvard Graduate School of Business Administration, A.W. Mellon Hall (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Harvard Law School (Box 42, Folder 8)
  - Home for Aged Protestants (Box 42, Folder 9)
  - Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania (Box 42, Folder 10)
  - Hoover Institution on War, Peace, and Revolution (Box 42, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, H (Box 42, Folder 12)
  - EDUCOM, Inter-university Communication Council (Box 42, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, I (Box 42, Folder 14)
  - Johns Hopkins University (Box 42, Folder 15-18)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, J (Box 42, Folder 19)
  - Kay Boys Club (Box 42, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, K (Box 42, Folder 21)
  - Latrobe Hospital (Box 42, Folder 22)
  - Valley School of Ligonier (Box 42, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, L (Box 42, Folder 24)
  - George Marshall Research Foundation (Box 42, Folder 25)
  - Medical Society of the State of Pennsylvania (Box 42, Folder 26-27)
  - Mellon Institute of Fundamental Research (Box 42, Folder 28)
  - Mellon Institute of Industrial Research, Fundamental Research Trust (Box 42, Folder 29)
  - Mellon Institute (Box 43, Folder 1-5)
  - A.W. Mellon Junior High School (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Mellon Park, Sixth and Smithfield (Box 43, Folder 7-8)
  - Mercy Hospital (Box 43, Folder 9)
  - Metropolitan Pittsburgh Educational Television Station -- WQED (Box 43, Folder 10-12)
  - WQED, Financial (Box 43, Folder 13)
  - WQED (Box 44, Folder 1-4)
  - A Modern Constitution For Pennsylvania, Inc. (Box 44, Folder 5-6)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, M (Box 44, Folder 7)
  - National Gallery of Art, Public Schools Art Project (Box 44, Folder 8)
  - National Council on Crime and Delinquency (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - National Information Bureau (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - National Library for the Blind (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Nacy Relief Society, Citizens' Committee (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - National Scholarship Service and Fund for Negro Students (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Negro Educational Emergency Drive (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Oakland Civic Center (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Oakland Junction and Panther Hollows (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, N-O (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Pittsburgh Economy League (Box 45, Folder 9-10)
  - Pennsylvania United Theological Seminary Foundation, Inc. (Box 45, Folder 11)
  - Pittsburgh
    - Bicentennial Association (Box 45, Folder 12-15)
    - Bicentennial Association (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Forestry Asscociation, "Good Outdoor Manners" (Box 46, Folder 2)
    - Playhouse, Vanguard Projects Division (Box 46, Folder 3)
    - Experiment (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Robert Frost Choirs (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Pittsburgh
    - Foundation (Box 46, Folder 6-8)
    - History and Landmarks Foundation (Box 46, Folder 9)
    - Hospital (Box 46, Folder 10)
    - New Friends of Music, Inc., Concert Artist Program (Box 46, Folder 11)
    - Opera, Inc. (Box 46, Folder 12)
    - Park and Playground Society (Box 46, Folder 13)
    - Plan for Art (Box 46, Folder 14)
    - Playhouse (Box 47, Folder 1-2)
    - Public Schools, Pittsburgh Leadership Seminar, Pittsburgh Scholar Program, State Aid to Urban Education, Director of Developmental Projects (Box 47, Folder 3)
    - Regional Planning Association, The Pittsburgh Center (Box 47, Folder 4)
    - Symphony (Box 47, Folder 5-6)
    - Symphony Society Endowment (Box 48, Folder 1)
    - Theological Seminary, Advanced Pastoral Studies (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Planned Parenthood Committee of Pittsburgh, Inc. (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Planning Foundation of America, American Institute of Planners, Pittsburgh Regional Chapter (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Presbyterian Association for the Care of the Aged and Orphans (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Presbyterian Hospital of Pittsburgh (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Princeton University, Conference on NATO (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Princeton University (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Public Auditorium Authority of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County (Box 48, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, P-R (Box 48, Folder 10-12)
  - St. John's College (Box 48, Folder 13)
  - School for Physically Handicapped Children (Box 48, Folder 14)
  - Shadyside Academy (Box 48, Folder 15)
  - South Side Hospital (Box 48, Folder 16)
  - Swarthmore College (Box 48, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, S-T (Box 48, Folder 18-19)
  - Urban Redevelopment Authority (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - United Fund of Allegheny County, Film Production (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - United States Committee for the Care of European Children, Inc. (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - U.S.O. Special Committee, Washington, D.C. (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Unity Presbyterian Church (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - University of Pennsylvania, Foreign Policy Research Institute (Box 49, Folder 6-11)
  - University of Pennsylvania, Plan to Develop Scientists in Medical Research (Box 49, Folder 12)
  - Urban America, Inc. (Box 49, Folder 13)
  - Urban Redevelopment Authority (Box 49, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, U-V (Box 50, Folder 1-2)
  - Washington and Jefferson College (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Washington Cathedral, Washington D.C. (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - Washington Home for Foundlings (Box 50, Folder 5)
  - Western Pennsylvania Conservancy, Project 70 (Box 50, Folder 6)
  - Citizen Committee for Project 70 (Box 50, Folder 7)
  - Western Pennsylvania Conservancy, Lilian McCahan Materials (Box 50, Folder 8)
  - Western Pennsylvania Conservancy, Planning Studies, "Know Your River Basin," Ohiopyle Project, Racoon Creek/Hickory Club Property, Fernliff Park, "Land and People," Manual on Outdoor Education, Slippery Rock Muddy Creek Project (Box 50, Folder 9)
  - Western Pennsylvania Conservancy, General (Box 50, Folder 10)
  - World Affairs Council (formerly Foreign Policy Association of Pittsburgh), Discussion Groups, World Affairs Forum, America (Box 50, Folder 11)
  - World Affairs Council, Reorganization (Box 50, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Contributions, W (Box 50, Folder 13)
  - Yale to Clare -- Clare to Yale (Box 50, Folder 14)
  - Yale Faculty Committee for Recieving Oxford and Cambridge University Children, Inc. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Yale University Press (Box 51, Folder 2)
  - Young Men and Women's Hebrew Association (Box 51, Folder 3)
  - University of Pittsburgh
    - Scholarships (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Graduate School of Public Health (Box 51, Folder 5-6)
    - Space Research Center (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Women's Education (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - Public Relations (Box 51, Folder 9)
    - Proposed School of Religion (Box 51, Folder 10)
    - Roberson Manuscript, Art in Pittsburgh, Barrax Manuscript (Box 51, Folder 11)
  - University Health Center
    - School of Preventive Medicine, Department of Preventive Medicine (Box 51, Folder 12)
    - Nurses Training School (Box 51, Folder 13)
    - School of Nursing (Box 51, Folder 14)
  - Graduate School of Public Health, Red Report, Dr. Lowell J. Reed (Box 51, Folder 15)
  - University Health Center
    - Presbyterian University Hospital (Box 51, Folder 16)
    - Vice Chancellor (Box 51, Folder 17)
  - University of Pittsburgh, Program for Academic Difficulties (Box 51, Folder 18)
  - Establishment of the College of the Academic Disciplines (Box 51, Folder 19)
  - Western Psychiatric Institute (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - Carnegie Mellon University Professor Grant and University of Pittsburgh Professorship (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - University of Pittsburgh Professorship Carnegie Mellon University (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Allegeheny River Project (Box 52, Folder 4)
  - Chatham College (Box 52, Folder 5)
  - Micellaneous Contributions, X-Z (Box 52, Folder 6)
- Mellon Estate, XV.
  - Receipt for Advancement (estate of A.W. Mellon, Deceased) (Box 52, Folder 7)
  - United States Treasury Department, Questionaires (Box 52, Folder 8)
  - Program for distribution for remaing A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Funds (Box 52, Folder 9)
  - Gifts of Art (Box 52, Folder 10)
  - Receipts for advancement from the estate of Andrew W. Mellon (Box 52, Folder 11)
  - Real Estate (Box 52, Folder 12)
  - Deed of gift to A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust by A.W. Mellon (Box 52, Folder 13)
  - Deeds of Trust, gift and distribution (Box 52, Folder 14)
  - Distribution from estate -- cash (Box 52, Folder 15)
  - Distribution from estate -- miscellaneous (Box 52, Folder 16)
  - Deed of Trust
    - Gift and distribution, December 30, 1930 (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - Agreement of, June 6, 1934 (Box 52, Folder 18)
    - Agreement of, June 30, 1945 (Box 52, Folder 19)
    - Agreement of, January 4, 1950 (Box 52, Folder 20)
  - 716 Jackson Place, N.W. Washington, D.C., 1937-1952 (Box 52, Folder 21)
  - Termination of Grants, general file (Box 52, Folder 22)
- Orphans Court Accounting, XVI.
  - Correspondence re: accounts filed with Orphans Court (Box 52, Folder 23)
  - Fifth Account, May 31, 1949-January 4, 1954 (Box 52, Folder 24)
  - Sixth Account, January 5, 1954-July 9, 1958 (Box 52, Folder 25)
  - Seventh Account, July 10, 1958-December 14, 1967 (Box 52, Folder 26)
- Mellon Family, XVII.
  - Mellon Family (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Mellon Family, Fortune article, October 1967 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - Mellon family file (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - A.W. Mellon: re portraits and photographs (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - Brief biographical sketch of A.W. Mellon (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - Mellon - R.K. Mellon's death, June 6, 1970 (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - Paul Mellon (Box 53, Folder 8)
  - A.W. Mellon file: Hendricks Manuscript (Box 53, Folder 9)
  - National Gallery - Mellon Collection - Paul Mellon's dedication speech (Box 53, Folder 10)
  - Yale Center for British Art (Box 53, Folder 11)
  - Dedication pamphlets (Box 53, Folder 12)
  - National Gallery, Clippings (Box 53, Folder 13)
  - National Gallery, East Building (Box 53, Folder 14)
  - Various Articles on Pittsburgh (Box 53, Folder 15)
- Institute for Philosophical Research, XVIII.
  - File 1-2 (Box 53, Folder 16-17)
- Trust Policy, XIX.
  - Seeking a Central Project -- A.W. Educational and Charitable Trust (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - Future Trust Policy (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - Work Papers, booklets (Box 54, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous Patman and Mellon Material, XX.
  - A.W. Mellon Education and Charitable Trust -- Reece and Dodd Committee (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - A.W. Mellon Education and Charitable Trust -- Cox Committee (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - Wright Patman Material (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - Wright Patman, inquiries, general correspondence (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - A.W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust Questionaires, Replies to Wright Patman inquiries 1-5 (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Wright Patman Inquiries, A.W. Mellon Education and Charitable Trust Questionaire 1, 1963-1969 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Foundations; United States Treasury Department, Wright Patman Committee (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - File Copy - Material and Information Frunished to the Honorable Wright Patman, House of Representatives, Washington, D.C., August 10, 1961 (Box 55, Folder 5)
- Contributions to the University of Pittsburgh, XXI.
  - Financial (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence Mellon Art Agreement, 1913 (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - American Philosophical Quarterly (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - British American Associates (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - Chancellor Litchfield (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - Civic Photographic Library, Financial (Box 56, Folder 1-2)
  - Commons Room (Box 56, Folder 3)
  - Computation and Data Processing Center (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - Core Curriculum Program (Box 56, Folder 5)
  - Office of Cultural and Educational Exchange, Council for International Visitors (Box 56, Folder 6)
  - English Room (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - Graduate School of Public and International Affairs (Box 56, Folder 8)
  - Graduate School of Public and International Affairs, Ditchley House (Box 56, Folder 9)
  - Proposed organization of graduate study (Box 56, Folder 10)
  - Inauguration Seminars (Box 56, Folder 11)
  - Institute of Local Governments (Box 56, Folder 12)
  - Institute of Public Administration, New York City, (Luther Gulick) (Box 56, Folder 13)
  - Law School
    - General File (Box 56, Folder 14)
    - Progress Reports (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - Financial (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - Model Housing Sanitation Ordinance (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - Learning Research and Development Center (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Study of the University Libraries Problem (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - University of Pittsburgh Library (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Gifts (Box 57, Folder 7)
  - Negro Scholarship Aid, NSSFNS, Summer Collegee Prepatory Program, and general (Box 57, Folder 8)
  - Oakland Colleges - relationships (Box 57, Folder 9)
  - Oakland Corporation (Box 57, Folder 10)
  - Oakland Corporation, Voting common stock (Box 57, Folder 11)
  - Philosophical Research Project - Reiser (Box 57, Folder 12)
  - Planning and Development (Box 57, Folder 13)
  - Potential Stories (Box 57, Folder 14)
- Program Materials, XXII.
  - American Wind Symphony (Box 57, Folder 15-16)
  - American Waterways (Box 58, Folder 1-2)
  - Center for the Arts
    - Center for the Arts (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - Middleheim (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - Banshaft Agreement (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - Estimates (Box 58, Folder 6)
  - Poetry Center (Box 58, Folder 7-8)
  - Poetry General (Box 58, Folder 9)
  - Bern Association (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Files for filing in the File Cabinets (Box 60, Folder 1)